Hi, I'm Apoorva Raji, and,
uh, I'm currently in my third year of Bachelor's degree in Computer
Science and Engineering with specialization in Artificial Intelligence and Machine
Learning, uh, from Vellore Institute of Technology.
Uh, I'm excited to share my project with you
today. In this project, I worked at the Upstox API to build a stock
option analysis tool. So,
uh, basically this tool helps,
to analyze option chains, calculate margin requirements,
and compute the premium earned for different options.
So, the project overflow can be divided into several parts.
First one is API authentication.
Second one is fetching option chain data.
Third one is data processing and analysis.
And the last and the most important step is margin and premium earned calculation.
So, let me walk you through, uh,
some of the key functions in the code. As you can see here,
uh, this is the code structure.
First one is API authentication and data retrieval.
So, here, uh, we have imported the dependencies,
pandas, numpy, and request.
And next step, we have, uh,
we have loaded the upstox API key and the secret key using .env
file in the Google full app. And the next step is to get authorization
key. So the authorization key is.
Uh, through the authorization key, we can get the access token.
So this is my redirect URL. Uh, and this is the URL
through which we are going to get the, uh,
authorization. So this output URL helps to get
this authorization key, which is this one.
And now this is the code to get the access token.
This is the URL from the upstox documentation to get the access token.
Thank you. And the data here we,
uh, added is code,
which is basically the authorization key client ID,
which is basically the upstox API key.
And the client, uh, RC, this is our secret key.
And this is a redirect URL. So,
uh, from this code,
we got the access token and we saved it here.
And this is the code to get the instrument.
so this instrument key is important so that we can get this
sound sample of, uh, different types of instrument key to retrieve the
data. Now, the next step is,
uh, fetch option chain data. So,
uh, the option chain data,
uh, is basically,
uh, we designed the function, the get option chain data function,
which retrieves data about various options,
both put and call for given instrument key,
let's suppose nifty. This data includes strike,
prices, open interest and bid ask prices,
which are important for any options to them.
So we can see here the code, uh,
this is the URL, uh,
from the upstops to get the option chain data and the parameters we use
here is instrument key and the expiry date instrument key I'm using here is
nifty and the expiry date is 14th of November,
2024. And the,
we got the output output is basically in the JSON format.
as you can see here. And the length of the output is 94.
So next step is data processing and option chain formatting.
So we have formatted the data we got from this code in
this particular format, which is basically how the option chain would look in
upstops. So these are the columns like column volume,
column IV, col, vega, gamma,
theta, delta, and so on. We have converted this into proper data frame,
as you can see.
This is the data we got after processing and formatting.
So, uh,
proceeding to the next step, which is,
uh,
to design the get option chain data. As we have seen,
we have, uh, retrieved the option chain data.
Now, uh, this function, this function basically,
uh, returns the higher bid price for put options that is PE or
the highest aspirate for all options that is CE for each strike price.
As you can see, this, uh, whole functions,
uh,
did this. And the instrument name I used
here is Nifty. And the result we got is.
For Nifty, for the strike price,
the side PE is,
and the bid ask is this. And the next step is margin and
calculation. So,
Margin and Premium Calculation, that is this function,
the calculate margin and premium, uh,
function calculates two key metrics. First one is margin required and second one
is premium required. So, uh,
margin required is based on the lot size and bid price.
And the premium earned is the total premium collected based on the bid prices.
So, this function, uh, basically helps to understand the financial commitment needed to
take a position in options and the potential returns.
Example, as you As can see here, the margin
calculation logic multiplies the lot size and applies the multiplier to
estimate the margin required to buy an option.
And the final result,
as we can see here, this is the final result.
For instrument key Nifty,
we got this margin and premium earned.
So, uh, one of the main challenges I faced during this project was handling
API rate limits and ensuring the data was phased correctly,
especially when, uh, dealing with large sets of market data.
I also needed to ensure that the data returned from the API was in
structure format or, uh, and proper processing and analysis should
be done so that, uh,
we get the data in proper format.
And then another challenge I was faced,
uh, and another challenge was to understand how margin calculation works for
options, like there are various factors involved such as lot size and option
types. It's a critical for making decisions in a real trading environment.
Um, and throughout this project,
I applied systematic approach to break down each problem and tackle it into one
step at a time. So the biggest insight I gained was how APS
can use to access real-time market data and make automated financial
decisions based on that data. So it helped me,
uh, realize that importance of clean data,
reliable communication and automation and making,
uh, real-time decisions. And the unique approach I used here is,
uh,
integrating the margin calculation logic and the premium earn formula,
both, both of which are crucial for option traders like for automate
by like by automating these calculations,
I've created tool that can potentially be expanded for broader market analysis
and which could assist traders in making real-time data-driven decisions.
Thank you for watching. I hope this video gave you,
uh, an insight into how I approached building this project.
I look forward to any feedback and opportunity to further discuss how I
can contribute to breakout AI as part of this Python development team.
Thank you.